A Finding Aid to the Harold Leeds Papers, 1940s-circa 2002, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Harold Leeds papers
1940s-circa 2002
Archives of American Art
Leeds, Harold E., 1913-2002
AAA.leedharo
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
The papers of architect Harold E. Leeds measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1940s-circa 2002. The letters found here are primarily from painter Loren MacIver writing from France, during which time Leeds looked after the home belonging to MacIver and her husband, poet Lloyd Frankenberg. While mainly logistical in nature, MacIver does describe aspects of her daily life in France, and her and Frankenberg's friendships with prominent figures including Margaret Barr, Elizabeth Bishop, Pierre Matisse, and James Johnson Sweeney. The photographs in the collection document Leeds' life with partner and documentary filmmaker Wheaton Galentine, and Leeds' work as an architect and interior design professor at Pratt Institute.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as two series
Missing Title
Series 1: Letters, 1950s-1970 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Photographic Material, 1940s-circa 2002 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Biographical / Historical
Harold E. Leeds (1913-2002) was an architect and professor of interior design at Pratt Institute in New York City. He designed the Paris Theater, the Caribe Hilton in San Juan, and Martha Graham's dance studio. In 1951, Leeds, along with his partner, documentary filmmaker Wheaton Galentine, purchased a house at 64 Perry Street in the West Village. His neighbors, the painter Loren MacIver and her husband, poet Lloyd Frankenberg lived at 61 Perry Street. During their extended stays in France, Leeds would look after their home.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated in 2014 by Harry Leeds' estate via Barry Skovgaard, executor.
Scope and Contents
The papers of architect Harold E. Leeds measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1940s-circa 2002. The letters found here are primarily from painter Loren MacIver writing from France, during which time Leeds looked after the home belonging to MacIver and her husband, poet Lloyd Frankenberg. While mainly logistical in nature, MacIver does describe aspects of her daily life in France, and her and Frankenberg's friendships with prominent figures including Margaret Barr, Elizabeth Bishop, Pierre Matisse, and James Johnson Sweeney. The photographs in the collection document Leeds' life with partner and documentary filmmaker Wheaton Galentine, and Leeds' work as an architect and interior design professor at Pratt Institute.
Architects -- New York (State) -- New York; Expatriate artists -- France; Architecture -- Study and teaching; Interior decoration; Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; France -- description and travel; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Pratt Institute -- Faculty; Barr, Margaret Scolari, 1901-1987; Frankenberg, Lloyd, 1907-1975; Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979; MacIver, Loren, 1909-; Galentine, Wheaton; Sweeney, James Johnson, 1900-; Matisse, Pierre, 1900-1989
- Letters, 1950s-1970; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Letters date from 1950s-1970 and are primarily from Loren MacIver to Harold Leeds, who was caretaker of her and her husband's home in the West Village during their stays in France. While mainly logistical in nature, MacIver does describe aspects of her daily life in France, and her and Frankenberg's friendships with prominent figures including Margaret Barr, Elizabeth Bishop, Pierre Matisse, and James Johnson Sweeney. MacIver typically signed the letters from herself and Frankenberg, using "L, L" or "LoLo" for Loren and Lloyd. A few other letters are found here, including one to Lloyd Frankenberg.
  - Loren MacIver, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Letters, undated, 1950s-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Other Letters, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photographic Material, 1940s-circa 2002; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Photographic material dates from 1940s-circa 2002 and includes hundreds of prints of Leeds and his partner Galentine, and about fifty negatives. Many are travel pictures from various trips they took together to Martha's Vineyard, Vermont, Sweden, London, and other destinations. Also found here are interior views of Leeds and Galentine's residences at 4 East 48th Street, 64 Perry Street, and 208 East 58th Street in Manhattan. Photographs of friends and others includes one print of MacIver and Frankenberg, several of Victoria Kent at Louise Crane's country home, and others.
  - Harold Leeds and Wheaton Galentine, 1940s-circa 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Harold Leeds at Pratt Institute, 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interiors, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Travel, 1945-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Friends and Others, 1950s-circa 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harold Leeds, Wheaton Galentine, and Others, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key; Negatives (Box 3, Folder 1)